
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Max Rath</title>
   <link>https://blog.mxrt.de/</link>
   <description>Recent content on Max Rath</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2021 - Maximilian Rath</copyright>
   <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
   
       <atom:link href="https://blog.mxrt.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Stable Reduction of Curves</title>
       <link>https://blog.mxrt.de/posts/stable-reduction-of-curves/</link>
       <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://blog.mxrt.de/posts/stable-reduction-of-curves/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;Five years  ago in the last year of my bachelor studies, while writing my thesis in algebraic geometry, I decided to take a seminar called&amp;ldquo;Stable Reduction Of Curves&amp;rdquo;. It seemed intriguing: prerequesites were basics of scheme theory (i.e. Chapter II and parts of Chapter III of Harthsorne)and so far I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen many applications of all that wondrous and intimidating machinery that is scheme based algebraic geometry to the realm of number theory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And see, that&amp;rsquo;s also kind of where the problems started: I hadn&amp;rsquo;t really seen much algebraic number theory so far. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even knowwhat quadratic reciprocity was! (And I still don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; know, if I&amp;rsquo;m being honest.) So even while I understood &amp;ldquo;my&amp;rdquo; small corner of the proof, I never really made sense of the big picture. Now, five years later (and, because I switched fields, with no additional algebraic geometry knowledge at my disposal), I&amp;rsquo;ll try to understand what exactly this was all about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The seminar was based on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/82106467.pdf&#34;&gt;paper by Artin and Winters&lt;/a&gt;, which (re-)proved the following theorem due to Deligne and Mumford:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;theorem&#34;&gt;    &lt;div class=&#34;theorem-header&#34;&gt;        &lt;strong&gt;Theorem (Stable Reduction of Curves).&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;    Let $C$ be a smooth proper curce of genus $g$ over the field of fractions $K$ of a discrete valuation ring $R$ with algebraically closed residue field $k$. There is a finite field extension $K&#39;$ of $K$ such that $C_{K&#39;}$ has stable reduction over the integral closure $R&#39;$ of $R$ in $K&#39;$.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though I knew most of the words, this still read like random jumble. Why on earth would anyone find this theorem interesting much less try to prove it?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, in the following, I will try to discover why the statement worth proving.Our journey starts with a equation which we would like to understand the solutions over $\mathbb{Q}$, such as$$ x^3 + y^3 = 8.$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homogeneous_polynomial&#34;&gt;homogenization&lt;/a&gt; we get$$\tag{1} x^3 + y^3 - 8z^3  = 0$$which cuts out a curve in the projective plane.It is a general principle in algebraic number theory (which we will take as given), that to understand an equation &lt;em&gt;globally&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. over $\mathbb{Q}$) one must understand them &lt;em&gt;locally&lt;/em&gt; first, i.e. at some prime $p$.Now if we reduce the above equation modulo $2$ we get$ x^3 + y^3 = 0$ (as an equation in $\mathbb{F}_2$); which, by the Jacobian criterion, is not smooth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we set $w \coloneqq 2z$ in $(1)$ then our equation becomes$$\tag{2} x^3 + z^3 - w^3 = 0,$$which stays smoot when reducing mod $2$.This substitution is an isomorphism over $\mathbb{Q}$. That is, we can recover rational solutions of $(1)$ from rational solutions of $(2)$ and vice versa.So for our original purpose of understanding the rational solutions, the two equations are basically the same, while the second one is much better behaved when reducing mod $2$.Speaking in the languague of schemes, we can collect all this information in a &lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt; of our curve $(1)$:&lt;div class=&#34;definition&#34;&gt;    &lt;div class=&#34;definition-header&#34;&gt;        &lt;strong&gt;Definition.  (Model of a curve $C$) &lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;    Let $C$ be a (normal, connected, projective) curve over $\mathbb{Q}$. A &lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt; of $C$ is a normal fibration$$ \mathcal{C} \to \operatorname{Spec}(\mathbb{Z}),$$together with an isomorphism$$ C \simeq \mathcal{C}_{\eta},$$where $\eta \in \operatorname{Spec}{\mathbb{Z}}$ is the  generic point.A &lt;em&gt;morphism of models&lt;/em&gt; is a morphism $\mathcal{C} \to \mathcal{C}&#39;$ that respects the isomorphism at the generic fiber.    &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So our two equations correspond to the models$$ \mathcal{C}_1 = \operatorname{Proj}\left(\mathbb{Z}[x,y,z]/\left(x^3 + y^3 - 8z^3\right)\right) \to \operatorname{Spec}{\mathbb{Z}}$$and$$ \mathcal{C}_2 = \operatorname{Proj}\left(\mathbb{Z}[x,y,z]/\left(x^3 + y^3 - z^3\right)\right) \to \operatorname{Spec}{\mathbb{Z}}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With isomorphic fibers over the generic point (i.e. when interpreted over $\mathbb{Q}$), but with diferent fibers over $2$.We say $\mathcal{C}$ has a &lt;strong&gt;good reduction&lt;/strong&gt; at a prime $p$, if the fibre over $p$ is &lt;em&gt;smooth&lt;/em&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;bad reduction&lt;/strong&gt; if it isn&amp;rsquo;t, i.e we get singularities when reducing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we could hope, given a smooth projective curve $C$ over $\mathbb{Q}$, to find a model $\mathcal{C}$ of $C$ such that it has good reduction at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; primes $p$. Alas, that is too much to hope. Still, there is some good news. First:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;theorem&#34;&gt;    &lt;div class=&#34;theorem-header&#34;&gt;        &lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;    The set of primes $p$ at which $\mathcal{C}$ has &lt;em&gt;bad reduction&lt;/em&gt; is finite.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, this is where stable reductions and the theorem of Deligne and Mumford comes in.A &lt;em&gt;stable&lt;/em&gt; reduction is one which is reduced and has at most &lt;em&gt;ordinary double points&lt;/em&gt;. These are singularities that look locally like the coordinate axes $xy=0$. Generally we can&amp;rsquo;t hope to do any better than that. Furthermore Deligne-Mumford tells us that we might have to extend our base field slightly and work in a finite extension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But wait, Deligne-Mumford theorem works over a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discrete_valuation_ring&#34;&gt;DVR&lt;/a&gt;, we are working over $\mathbb{Z}$, how does that work? Well, if we &amp;ldquo;zoom in&amp;rdquo; at one of the primes $p$ of bad reduction, i.e. we localize at the point $(p)$, we get $\mathbb{Z}_{(p)}$, a DVR.Stated in its full generality the theorem works in the setting of a relative curve over a &lt;em&gt;Dedekind Scheme&lt;/em&gt;. A Dedekind Scheme is a scheme that looks locally like the spectrum of a Dedekind Ring, which in turn is a ring that yields a DVR when localized at a closed point.By localizing at the finitely many bad reductions (and reducing to the case of a algebraically closed fraction field) we arrive at the heart of the matter as stated at the beginning of this post.(This reduction can for example be found in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.de/Algebraic-Geometry-Arithmetic-Graduate-Mathematics/dp/0199202494&#34;&gt;Liu&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When stated in this generality we can apply Deligne-Mumford to other situations as well. Take for example a family of curves over some field $k$ with a parameter t:$$ y^2 = x(x-1)(x-t) $$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This gives a relative curve$$ \mathcal{C} \to \operatorname{Spec}(k[t]) $$Whose fibers over $0$ and $1$ degenerate to &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; singular curves since the right hand side has a double zero at $0$ resp. $1$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I still don&amp;rsquo;t understand a whole lot of things about this theorem (and practically nothing about its proof), I can finally see how it might be a worthwile result to study. Who knows, maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll even read a book on basic algebraic number theory next.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
